<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The profe and declaration of thys proposition: fayth only iustifieth: gathered [and] set forth by Richarde Tracy</title>
            <title>Profe and declaration of thys proposition: fayth only justifieth.</title>
            <author>Tracy, Richard, d. 1569.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1543</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 55 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 33 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A13857</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 24164</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S104938</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99840668</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99840668</idno>
            <idno type="VID">5195</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A13857)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 5195)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 155:03)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The profe and declaration of thys proposition: fayth only iustifieth: gathered [and] set forth by Richarde Tracy</title>
                  <title>Profe and declaration of thys proposition: fayth only justifieth.</title>
                  <author>Tracy, Richard, d. 1569.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[64] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>E. Whitchurch,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1543?]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Imprint from STC.</note>
                  <note>Running title reads: Of iustification.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-D.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Faith --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-11</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:5195:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5195:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>The profe and declaration of thys propoſition: Fayth only iuſtifieth: gathered &amp; ſet-forthe by Richarde Tracy.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="preface">
            <pb facs="tcp:5195:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5195:2"/>
            <head>The preface.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>¶To the moſte chryſten and vyctoriouſe prynce, Henry the .viii. by the grace of God, kynge of Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land, Fraunce and Irelande, Defen<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dour of the faith, and of the churche of England, and alſo of Irelande, in earthe, the ſupreme head: Rycharde Tracy wyſſheth long continuaunce of health, proſperouſe ſucceſſe, and lyfe eternall.</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">M</seg>Oſte vyctorious prynce, and pru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent gouernour, godly vnitie, con<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>corde, and loue, is moſt prayſed, ſet fourthe, and taught, thorough the hole courſe of the holye ſcriptures, as to your ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſtie it is rygh well knowen: fyrſte taught by the prophete, ſayenge:</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5195:3"/>
            <p>Beholde howe goodly and pleaſant it is,<note place="margin">Pſalme .cxxii</note> that brethern dwel togyther in one vnitie. Chriſte alſo prayd to his father,<note place="margin">Iohn .xvii,</note> ſayeng: Holye father in thy name preſerue them, whome thow haſt geuen me, that they may be one as we be. The apoſtle exhorteth, and prayeth al men, that they be dili<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gent to kepe the vnitie of the ſpirite,<note place="margin">Epheſ. iiii.</note> in the bonde of peace, beyng one bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>die, and one ſpirite, euen as they be called in one hope. Let there be but one lorde, one faythe, one baptyme, one god and father of vs all &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Seyng than that Chryſte, the pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>phete, and the apoſtle, exhorte, and commaunde, ſuche a chriſtian vnitie to be had, and kepte in the catholyke churche, and alſo conſyderynge the peynfull trauayle, ſtudie, and great charges, whiche your maieſtie hath ſuſteyned, and dayly doth ſuſteyne,
<pb facs="tcp:5195:3"/> not onely to preſerue vnitie amonge your louyng ſubiectes, but alſo to a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>voyde, and vtterly remoue, all occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiones, whiche myghte be cauſe, or meane of diuiſion, or breche of ſuch chriſten vnitie, therefore I moſt ſim<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ple of this your realme, and yet one of the lyuely membres of this your ciuile, and polityke bodie, hearynge diuiſion, and diuerſitie of opinions, among your louyng ſubiectes, con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cernyng one of the moſte principall, and neceſſarye articles of our fayth, whiche is, that faithe onely iuſtify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: can not but lament and bewail, ſuch diuiſion, in ſo godlie, and neceſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſary an article, which is the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and grounde of all the chriſten religion.</p>
            <p>For the godlye vnderſtandyng of the ſayde article, well taſted, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardlye perceyued, is the quyetnes
<pb facs="tcp:5195:4"/> of euerye conſcience, oppreſſed with any kynde of aduerſitie, other ſpiri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuall or temporall, yea the onely an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ker and refuge in the extreme agonie and panges of death. wherfore with all the poore knowledge whiche god hath geuen to me, I haue diligently by the auctorities of holye ſcripture, ſet forth and declared, the true ſenſe, meanyng and vnderſtandyng of the ſayde article and propoſition, moſte humblye deſyrynge your hyghneſſe, more to ponder my good wylle, and feruent deſyre, to profit many, than my rude and barbarouſe ſettynge fo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rthe of this lytle treatiſe, whiche I ſubmit moſte lowlye, vnto your gra<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiouſe, and godly iudgement, to the whiche if this my labour, and ſtudy ſhall be thought profitable for youre chriſten congregation, I than moſt mekely eftſones deſyre your maieſty
<pb facs="tcp:5195:4"/> that it maye be put forth, to the glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye of god, your honour and the vti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lytie of all your louyng ſubiec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes. And I ſhall dayly pray to god, that he wyl vouch<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſafe, to ſtrengthen you with his holy ſprite thoroughly to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourme a godly reformation in Chriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes churche, within your dominions, with good proſperitie, in all your affaye<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb facs="tcp:5195:5"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:5195:5"/>
            <head>Of iuſtification.</head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">F</seg>Or as moche, as the moſte neceſſary arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle of chriſten religi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is, that fayth one lye iuſtifieth, which the vngodlye do day<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly preache agaynſte, and obſcure by many wayes, I haue thought ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore very expedient, in this litle trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> holye ſcriptures,<note place="margin">By mercy <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> fayth, ſinne<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> be purified, by the feare of god all ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> declyne from euyll. Prouerb. xv</note> to declare the ryght ſence, and true vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dyng therof, which is, that the mercy and fauour, of God iuſtifieth: whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che mercie and fauour, we onely by fayth obteyne, beleuyng conſtantly the promeſſes of goddes mercy, and fauour made vnto vs. And the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture ſayeth, that this fayth,<note place="margin">Epheſ. ii.</note> whyche onely iuſtifieth, is onelye the worke of god in vs, and co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meth, not by a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye mannes power, wiſedome, ler<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning, nor that god geueth it, becauſe
<pb facs="tcp:5195:6"/> of any vertue, or vertuous diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, which he ſeeth in man, nor that anye man can prepare hym ſelfe, or make hym ſelfe apte and meete, to re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceiue this fayth, but god geueth this fayth frely, without any reſpecte or regarde to any good wyl, good wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes, or good diſpoſition, before by god ſene in ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath, xii.</note> For y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture ſayth other make the tre good, and his fru<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>yte good alſo, or els make the tree euill, &amp; his fruyte euyll alſo.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>d did firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> vpon A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ll and after <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> his giftes. Geneſis. iiii.</note>Euen ſo man muſte fyrſte be made good, thoroughe fayth, before anye of his workes can be good. Ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore I ſaye that before this lyuelye faythe be gyuen from god to manne that he neyther hathe, nor can haue other good wyll, good workes, or godlye diſpoſition to doe good. For without this lyuely faythe, it is im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to pleaſe god.<note place="margin">Hebr. xii.</note> Wherefore
<pb facs="tcp:5195:6"/> faith muſte nedes fyrſte be gyuen of god, wherby the wyl is made good &amp; vertuous, before that any worke, whiche ſpringeth oure of the wylle, can be eyther good, or vertuous, as ſaynt Auguſtine ſayeth.<note place="margin">Auguſtyne v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the .cx. pſalme.</note> Verylye a man can not worke iuſtice, excepte he be iuſtified, but he that beleuethe in him, which iuſtifieth the wicked, begynneth of fayth, ſo that the good workes that go before, do not ſhewe what he hath deſerued, but ſuch as folowe,<note place="margin">Auguſtine v<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon the .lxvii.</note> ſhewe what he hath recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved. Alſo the ſame doctour ſayethe, Me thynketh that the fayth is to be prayſed, whiche goeth before woor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, for wythout y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> merites of good workes, thorough fayth, the wicked is iuſtified, as the apoſtle fayethe: To the beleuyng in hym, whiche iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifieth the wycked, his fayth is cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted for iuſtice: that from thenſeforth
<pb facs="tcp:5195:7"/> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame faith may begin to worke by loue. For they onelye oughte to be called good workes, whiche be done for the loue of god. To ſuche woor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes, it is neceſſarie that faythe ſhuld goe before, that frome this faythe, theſe woorkes: and not frome theſe workes that faythe ſhulde begynne. For no man worketh for the loue of god, except he fyrſte beleue in god.</p>
            <p>Alſo the ſame doctour ſayeth vppon this texte:<note place="margin">Rom. ii.</note> They are not rightuous which heare the lawe, but they whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che doe the lawe, ſhall be iuſtified: That is as moche to ſaye, that we maye knowe them,<note place="margin">Aug. in the booke of the ſpryte and the letter the .xxvi chapter.</note> not to be the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers of the lawe, except they be iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fied: Not that iuſtification ſhoulde come to the doers, but that iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion ſhulde go before the doers.</p>
            <p>Here by theſe auctorities, of ſaint Auguſtyne, it is manifeſt and playn
<pb facs="tcp:5195:7"/> that no workes be good, except thei ſpryng out of a lyuyng faythe. Not withſtandyng ſome I thynke, wyll be offended with this my ſayeng, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God geueth not faith whiche onely iuſtifieth to any man, bicauſe of any vertue or vertuouſe diſpoſition whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che he before ſeeth in man: for they thinke that God, whiche euer hathe ſeene all thynges preſentely, dyd ſee before in Peter, Paule, Dauyd, Maria Magdalene, and ſuch other theyr repentynge hartes: And alſo theyr godly diſpoſitions, wherwith they woulde mekelye, obedientlye, and wyllynglye conſente to goddes ſpirituall motions, and grace offred to them, vſynge and exerciſyng, the gyftes and talentes, by god gyuen to them accordynglye. Whiche dyſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſition, and vertuous workynge, accordynge to theyr callyng, before
<pb facs="tcp:5195:8"/> they were preſently by god ſeen in them, dyd prouoke and moue God (thynke they) to iuſtifye them.</p>
            <p>To all men of this ſtraunge opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion, I anſwere that ſaynt Iames ſayth: Erre not my deare brethern, euery good gifte, and euery parfect gyfte, is from aboue, and commeth downe from the father of lyght.</p>
            <p>Is euery good thynge come downe from the father of light? what haue they then, that they haue not recey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ued?<note place="margin">i. Corint. iiii.</note> If they haue receyued theym, why reioyce they as they had not re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyued them? what wyſe man pray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeth a ſtone for his ſwyfte flyeng in the ayre, whiche is caſte with vyo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence, whoſe nature is to lye ſtyll, yf it be not remoued. Lyke prayſe is to be giuen vnto vs for our good diſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>poſitions, and well workyng, whi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>che onely is wrought in vs, agynſt
<pb facs="tcp:5195:8"/> our nature, by the myght and grace of God, who worketh onely in vs, bothe the good wylle,<note place="margin">Philip. iiii.</note> and to per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fourme the ſame, without whome, we can doe nothyng, that good is.<note place="margin">Iohn. xv.</note>
            </p>
            <p>And for my parte I knowe noo ſcriptures, whiche do encourage a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nye man to thynke, that theyr good workes, or godlye diſpoſition to do good, by god before ſeene in theym, ſhulde moue god to iuſtifie them, or to endewe them with his grace and fauour. And than thus to deuyne,<note place="margin">Rom. xi. who gaue hi<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> firſt that he ſhulde recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pence hym a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gayne.</note> ſearche or iudge the cauſes mouing god, to geue his godly gyftes, with out his woorde, the ſame teachyng prouyng, and teſtifienge, is rather of curioſitie and of vayne opinion, than of any godlye perſwaſion, or holſome doctrine. For god by his prophete Eſaye ſayth:<note place="margin">Eſay. lii Rom x.</note> I am found of them that ſought me not, &amp; haue
<pb facs="tcp:5195:9"/> appeared to them, that axed not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter me. And agaynſt Iſraell he ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth: All daye long I haue ſtretched out my handes, vnto a people that beleueth not, but ſpeaketh agaynſt me. By this texte appearethe but ſmall prouocation, or good diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, mouyng god to gyue his god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly gyftes. And other knoweledge, than by this his woorde, haue we none. For whoe hath knowen the mynde of the lorde,<note place="margin">Rom xi.</note> or who was his counſellour, or who hathe gyuen to hym fyrſte, that he myght be recom<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>penſed agayne, for of hym, and tho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rough hym, and by hym, be all the thynges, to hym be glorye &amp;c.</p>
            <p>Where they thynke that god, for the good diſpoſition and godly ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, before ſeen in man, doth iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fye man: Verilye they be to moche forgetfull, of the corruption and poi<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſon
<pb facs="tcp:5195:9"/> of our nature whych is become ſo weake &amp; ſimple that in it can not be perceaued &amp; fou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de any ſuch good diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; godly vertues to moue God, to iuſtifye vs.<note place="margin">Math. vii.</note> For euell trees can not brynge forth any ſuch good frutes. Alſo the prophete ſayeth,<note place="margin">Pſalm. cxliii.</note> en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter not into iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, wyth thy ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uaunt, o Lorde, for in thy ſyghte no man lyuynge ſhalbe iuſtifyed.<note place="margin">Pſalm .cxxix.</note> Alſo yf thou wylt be extreme, to marke what is done amys, o Lorde, who maye abyde it,<note place="margin">Rom. iii.</note> for wythout dout all haue ſynned, and are deſtitute of the glorye of God. Where is then they, reioycyng excluded, by what law?<note place="margin">Galath. iii.</note> of vertuous good dyſpoſition, or good dedes? Naye, ſayeth Paule, but by the lawe of fayth. Wherfore there is nother thoughte, wyll, nor worke in vs, yf we co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſyder, and pon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der their goodnes in nature, where
<pb facs="tcp:5195:10"/> of we ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> take any occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to reioyce, but rather haue cauſe to lamente, &amp; to ſay with Iob,<note place="margin">Ioh. ix.</note> I feare all my wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes, bycauſe they be euyll.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Gene. viii.</note>Alſo the ſcripture ſayeth, the ima<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gination of mans harte, is euell eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from hys youthe. Item all mannes imaginatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thoughtes of hys harte are only euell euery daye.<note place="margin">Gene. vi.</note> It were therfore neceſſary, fyrſt to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ue our workes good, &amp; alſo a god<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly dyſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in vs to do good, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>vnto all the ſcripture wytneſſeth the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary, before y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we can proue, that our good workes, &amp; godly dyſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion before ſene in vs by God, do prouoke and moue God to iuſtifye vs, and to gyue vs hys grace and fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uoure. Yea although there were a godlye dyſpoſition in vs, yet that ſhulde not moue God, nor prouoke him to iuſtify vs: for Abraham was
<pb facs="tcp:5195:10"/> not iuſtifyed, bycauſe he offered his ſonne, and was alſo obedient to ſley hym, but bycauſe he beleued, ſayeth the ſcripture. Alſo Paule ſayeth,<note place="margin">Rom. xi.</note> Iſrael hath not obtayned y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> thynge whyche he ſought for: noo, but yet the election hath obtayned it. And by what meanes, ſayeth Paule, eue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> throughe the election of grace.<note place="margin">Ibidem.</note> The<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is it not by the deſeruynge of wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, of vertuoſe, or of good dyſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were grace and fauour, no grace, &amp; fauoure. Therfore hath God wrapped all nations in vnbe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lefe, that he myght haue mercye on all.</p>
            <p>And y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcripture wytneſſeth more ouer, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god ſayd to Moyſes,<note place="margin">xod<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>. xxxiii.</note> I wyl ſhewe mercy, to whom I ſhewe mer<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cy, I wyll haue compaſſion, on who<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> I haue compaſſion. So ſayeth Paule, lyeth it not, in a mannes
<pb facs="tcp:5195:11"/> wyll,<note place="margin">Rom. ix.</note> or runnynge, but in the mercy of God.<note place="margin">Rom. v.</note> In this God ſetteth out his loue towardes vs, ſayeth Paule, ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ynge that, whyle we were yet ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners, Chriſt dyed for vs. Alas what good dyſpoſition, vertue, or good worke was in vs beyng ſynners, to moue, or to ſtyrre god to iuſtifye vs, or to ſhewe vs any grace,<note place="margin">Ierem. xxxii.</note> or fauour, ſurely none. But the very true cauſe was onely hys eternall loue, where wyth he loued vs. Wherfore he ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berallye, and frelye dyd drawe vs, moued onelye wyth hys mercye, to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>warde vs, as ſaynt Iames ſayeth.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Iames .i.</note>Of hys owne frewyll begat he vs, wyth the worde of lyfe. Yf our rege<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neration came by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> free wyl of god, the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was he not moued bi our good dyſpoſition, vertue, nor good wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes before ſene by God of vs. And therfore Paule wyllyng our helth,
<pb facs="tcp:5195:11"/> and ſaluation to be certen, &amp; ſure tea<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cheth vs y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> our iuſtification hangeth nother of the workes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe, nor of our good dyſpoſition, vertuoſe or good workes, but only on fayth, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it may come of fauour and grace, and that the promyſe myght be ſure, for ſo Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> was made ſtronge in the fayth, &amp; gaue honour to god,<note place="margin">Rom. iiii.</note> ſtedfa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtly beleuyng, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he which had made the promys, was able alſo to make it good. And therfore was it rekned to him for rightwyſnes. This was not wrytre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> only for Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, but al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo for vs, that we ſhulde grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de, ſta<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>blyſhe, &amp; make ſure our ſaluatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on goddes promiſes, whych be euer certeyn &amp; ſure. So that in all temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations of deſperation, we may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tly, &amp; ſurely truſt to that ſure pro<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>myſe made by god to vs. The ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture therfore geueth all the power
<pb facs="tcp:5195:12"/> of iuſtifycation, only &amp; holly to god, whych by hys prophete Eſay ſayth,<note place="margin">Ezaie. xliii.</note> I am he, I am he onelye, whyche for myne owne ſelfe ſake, do awaye thyne offence, &amp; forget thy ſynnes, ſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> I wyl neuer thynke vpon them Alſo the prophet O ſee ſayeth:<note place="margin">O<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ee. xiii.</note> O Iſ<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rael thyne iniquitie hath deſtroyed the, but in me onely, is thy helpe.</p>
            <p>Therfore the chriſten mans iuſtice, wherby he is accepted before God, to be iuſte, &amp; ryghtwyſe, is not a ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uill iuſtice, &amp; earthly iuſtice, but an heue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ly iuſtice, not an actiue iuſtice, conſyſtynge in workes, whyche we yelde, and gyue to god, but a paſſiue iuſtice, whych we receaue of mercy, onely fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god. For god ſeeth in vs no goodnes nor any other thyng, wher<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>by he is moued to fauour vs, but on<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye our wretched myſery, wherby he is moued wyth hys godly benigni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie,
<pb facs="tcp:5195:12"/> and pytie to haue mercy on vs.</p>
            <p>wherfore our iuſtice is not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>in vs nor of vs, but Chriſt is oure iuſtice,<note place="margin">Chriſt ieſꝰ of God is made vnto vs wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome and al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo rightuouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes. &amp; ſatiſfi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing &amp; redemci<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>on, that accor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dynge as it is written, he y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> reioyceth, ſhu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lde reioyce in the lorde.</note> being w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out vs, &amp; he is frelye w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>out our deſeruing, gyuen to vs, by God. It is nothyng of our worthynes, or deſeruynge, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Chriſtes iuſtice is cal<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>led our iuſtice, but of Chriſtes onely infinite mercy, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he eſtemeth &amp; reke<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth hys iuſtice to be ours. So that we ſynners, couered, &amp; clothed with chriſtes iuſtice,<note place="margin">i. Cor. i.</note> do appere in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſyght of god iuſte, &amp; ryghteous, &amp; ſo of god for Chriſtes ſake be accepted, as iuſt &amp; ryghteous. Alas then, what vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynde, frowarde, &amp; ſtyffenecked peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple be we, which wyl not moſte me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kely, lowly, and thankefully, accept, receyue, and take Chriſtes iuſtice, ho<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lynes, and redemption lyberaly, fre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, &amp; moſt mercyfully offred, &amp; geuen vnto vs of god, wherby we without
<pb facs="tcp:5195:13"/> cauſe of our parte deſerued, ſhuld be eſtemed, reputed, and accepted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him, notwithſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ding our weak<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nes, &amp; ſynfulnes, to be therof forge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, &amp; eſtemed, as iuſt, &amp; holy in hys ſyght, for Chriſtes ſake only. what vntha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>kfulnes, &amp; vnkindnes is this, to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tempne goddes moſt mercyful aboundau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, &amp; lyberal gyftes, offered &amp; gyuen to vs? what arrogancy and preſumption is thys, to attribute, &amp; gyue to our weake, &amp; ſynful workes that helpe, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>forte, fauoure, &amp; reme<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dye, whych we onely by all equitie haue cauſe, &amp; be bou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>de to ſech, deſyre &amp; loke for, fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> god, for chriſtes paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; deathes ſake, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pryce of our ſynne &amp; only cauſe of our acceptau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce to fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uour? Thys vnworthy eſtimatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of workes, geuyng to the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi>, which god promiſed to gyue vs frely, is no leſſe then to iudge, &amp; eſteme God vntrue
<pb facs="tcp:5195:13"/> in all hys promyſes, whyche is, to confeſſe hym in worde, and to deny hym in deede, &amp; an vtter falſifyeng, &amp; denyal of al the ſcriptures. What vnwyſe, yea, &amp; mad me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be we, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che wyl ſtabliſhe, &amp; grou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d our ſalua<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon our vnperfyt, inco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtant, &amp; tranſitorie workes, rather the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vpon goddes mercy, to vs frelye promy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed? whych promyſe is euer co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtant ſure, &amp; infallibly true. What quiet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes can that conſcience haue, which hangeth hys helth, and lyfe euerla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtynge vpon inſtable, and vnperfyt workes of man, whyche peryſh and vaniſhe awaye, lyke the ſhadowes? Wherfore the ioye, and comfort of all Chryſten hertes is, that Chryſte is become our iuſtice, holynes, and redemption, whych we apprehende receaue, and accepte to be ours, by the lyberall gyfte of god, thorough
<pb facs="tcp:5195:14"/> faythe in hys promyſes onlye, and by no other meanes.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Note well the true vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
                  <g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>dyng &amp; mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nyng that fai<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>the only iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fieth.</note>And therfore we ſaye, that faythe onlye iuſtifiethe, whan we ſpeake vnder thys fourme, by faythe we be iuſtified, or by fayth we be frelye iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified, or that fayth onlye iuſtifieth. For al theſe ſentences be of one lyke force, vertue, or meanynge.</p>
            <p>We do not meane thereby, that faythe ſo alone iuſtifieth, that theſe wordes alone, and frelye exclude other good workes, or godlye ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues, that they be not ioyned wyth fayth, which neuer is without both good workes, &amp; vertuouſe, but, we by theſe wordes frelye, and only, do vtterlye exclude all opinion, truſte, &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fidence to our merites, vertues, dignitie, good diſpoſition, or wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thynes, that they in no wyſe be eſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, thought, or iudged, to be cauſe,
<pb facs="tcp:5195:14"/> meane, motion, or help, or to be part<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>lye cauſe, meane, motion, or help, to our iuſtification, whyche only, and holye we yelde, and gyue to God, &amp; to hys ſonne Ieſu Chriſt our Lord, which only is our hole, and ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t iuſtice, ſatiſfaction, and peacemaker for ſynne, wythout anye reſpecte to any good motion or godlye diſpoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, before by god ſeen in vs. And therefore who ſoeuer iudgeth or thynketh good workes, vertuouſe or godlye diſpoſition, to be anye cauſe, or helpe, or anye parte of cauſe, whereby God is moued, or ſtyred to iuſtifie vs, the ſame obſcu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth, and wythdraweth the glorye of God, and robbeth Chryſte of the honoure, by hym onelye deſerued, and to hym only due. Who cauſed hys prophete Danyell to ſaye.<note place="margin">Daniel .i,</note> To y<hi rend="sup">e</hi>, o Lord, al rightuoſneſſe belo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>geth,
<pb facs="tcp:5195:15"/> to vs perteynethe nothynge,<note place="margin">Note well what true iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtification is and what we be after iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.</note> but ſhame. whan God hathe freelye of hys onlye mercye, and fauour iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed vs, yet, we remayne ſynners. For the whych we muſt dayly pray wyth the ſayntes to god for pardo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and forgyuenes. For iuſtificacyon takethe not awaye ſynne, ſo that it remayneth not in vs, but iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion is properlye fre pardon, and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſyon of ſynnes, a couerynge of our ſynnes, a not rekening &amp; layeng them to our charge, onlye through the mercy, that we obteyne by faith in Chryſtes bloode, as the prophete ſayth,<note place="margin">Pſalm .xxxi.</note> bleſſed be they, whoſe ſynnes be forgyuen, whoſe offences be co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uered. And bleſſed is that man, to whome god imputeth not hys ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes.<note place="margin">For god was in chriſte, and made agrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment betwen the worlde and him ſelf, &amp; imputed no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> theyr ſinnes vnto them .ii. Cor. v.</note> whyche remiſſyon, couerynge, and not imputynge of ſynne, were in vayne, yf there were no ſynne in
<pb facs="tcp:5195:15"/> vs. For other our good workes and godlye diſpoſitions do ſatiſfye the lawe, or they do not ſatiſfye the lawe. If they ſatiſfye the lawe, we haue no nede than of Chryſtes iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice, to be imputed to vs. For yf ryghteouſnes come of the lawe, tha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is Chryſte deade in vayne,<note place="margin">Galat. i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> ſaythe paule. To ſuche therfore wythout dout, Chryſte is dead in vayne. And yf we do not ſatiſfie the lawe, than be we ſynfull,<note place="margin">Iames i. Curſes is eue<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rye man, that co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinueth not in al thinges, whiche are written in the booke to ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyl them. Galath iii.</note> and moue not god to iuſtifie vs. For yf we offende in one iote of the law, we than tranſgreſſe the hole lawe, ſo ſayth. S. Iames. Paul ſaith, I knowe nought by my ſelfe, yet am I not thereby iuſtified. If Paul knowynge nothynge by hym ſelfe, yet was not therby iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fyed, what meaneth it,<note place="margin">Cor. iiii.</note> that wha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> we examyne, &amp; trye our ſelfe, fyndynge oure ſelfe gyltie of the hole lawe,
<pb facs="tcp:5195:16"/> knowynge and felynge alſo in oure ſelfes an euyll diſpoſition, &amp; ſynne, ſhulde thynke wythout cauſe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> we haue godly diſpoſitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and vertues, mouyng god to iuſtifie vs? Not w<hi rend="sup">t</hi>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtandyng alſo y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the ſcriptures ſpea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kyng of iuſtification,<note place="margin">Rom. iii.</note> declare it to be frelye gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſayeng al haue ſynned, &amp; are deſtitute of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> glory of god, but are iuſtified frely, by his grace, tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> redemptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> that is in Chriſt Ieſu, whom God hath ſet forth to be the obteyner of mercye, through faith, by the meanes of his bloode. who can more plainly ſet forth, the true and ryght order of iuſtificatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>?<note place="margin">Eſai. xliii.</note> Alſo the prophete Eſaye ſaith: Put me nowe in remembraunce, for we will reaſon together, &amp; ſhewe what thou haſt, for to make y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryghtuouſe Thy fyrſt father offended ſore, and thy rulers haue ſynned againſt me.
<pb facs="tcp:5195:16"/> By thys text it is manifeſte, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> God reproueth al ſuch, which thynk that they haue any thyng, to moue God to iuſtifie the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, or to endowe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> hys grace, &amp; fauour. And therfore if any ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> truſt to his own merites or partly to chryſt, &amp; partly to his own merites, &amp; not holye, and onelye to Chriſtes merites, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame diſhonou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth God,<note place="margin">Deuter xviii.</note> whiche dyd ſende to vs Chriſt, whiche only is a ſufficie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uiour, &amp; beſydes hym, there is no ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uiour. And he doth much iniurie al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo to Chriſtes bloode, &amp; vtterly wa<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſure affiaunce &amp; co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſtant truſt, to haue remiſſion of his ſynnes only for Chryſtes bloode ſhed. Whych ly<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uely fayth onelye iuſtifieth.</p>
            <p>And therfore let all Chryſte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> men gyue the glory, &amp; honour of iuſtifica<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tion only, &amp; holye to God, to whom only it is due. And then alſo let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <pb facs="tcp:5195:17"/> confeſſe them, wyth the penytent, &amp; miſerable publicane, to be ſynners, and al their workes to be vnperfyt, ne leſte they be condempned wyth the proude phareſai.<note place="margin">Luke .v.</note> Remembryng euer that the hole haue no nede of a phiſicion,<note place="margin">Math. ix.</note> 
               <note place="margin">Luke. v.</note> but the ſycke. And Chryſt came not to calle the righteouſe,<note place="margin">Math. v.</note> but ſynners to repentaunce.<note place="margin">Luke .i.</note> The hun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grye, and thyrſty for ryghtuouſnes, Chryſt called bleſſed, and fulfylleth them with good thynges. And they whyche thynke them ſelues riche ynough of good merites, God put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth them awaye emptie, and voyde of all goodnes, as it apeareth in the Apocalipſis, where it is wrytten: I woll vomyt the out of my mouthe, bycauſe thou ſayſt, I am riche, and encreaſed wyth goodnes, and haue neade of nothyng, and knoweſt not howe thou arte wretched, and miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable,
<pb facs="tcp:5195:17"/> poore, blynde, &amp; naked. I cou<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cell the, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> thou bye of me, gold tried in the fyer, that thou mayſt be riche. wherfore, a meke &amp; lowlye co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſion of all our thoughtes, workes, &amp; dea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des, to be vnperfyght, whereby we earneſtlye repent, leaue, and forſake all truſt, and confidence in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and then to flye to Chriſte, truſtynge to goddes promyſe made to vs of re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of al our ſynnes, for Chriſtes ſake, is a ſure, and ſafe meane, and waye taught by the holye ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res, to haue remiſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our ſynnes. whyche ſaythe, repente and beleue. For where is no repentaunce, there is no belefe. And where as true repentaunce is, there is a conſtaunt affiaunce, and ſuer vnfayned truſte in goddes promyſe made to vs. whiche lyuely faythe onelye appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hendeth goddes fauoure, and mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cye,
<pb facs="tcp:5195:18"/> whereby we be iuſtified. And thys lyuely fayth bryngeth wyth it the holy gooſt, whyche renewythe mannes harte, and ſtyreth hym to loue, and to obeye the wyll of God. It cauſeth the harte to be meeke, lowelye, pacient in aduerſitie, libe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall to hys neyghbour in hys neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſitie, ſober, iuſte, fearynge God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuallye, ſtudiouſe to mortifie the fleſhe, and to auoyde al occaſions of ſynne. And thys lyuyng fayth con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinuallie ſteryth, and enforceth the mynde, wyth greate luſte, and cou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage to reſyſte ſynne, and all her oc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>caſions. And in concluſion, thys ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uyng fayth, moueth the minde with as hote and feruent deſyre, to acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyſſhe and to fulfyll, the good wyl of god, as euer the minde was deſy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>rous and ſtudyouſe, to execute, and to fulfylle his owne carnalle concu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>piſcence,
<pb facs="tcp:5195:18"/> and euyll luſtes.</p>
            <p>Wherefore all ſuche as heare or reade goddes worde, and thynke al ſuche thynges wrytten therin to be true, and yet not fealyng the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſelues chaunged, nor no newe affections, &amp; deſyres in theyr hartes ſprongen vp to loue God, &amp; to mortifie y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> fleſh, haue not yet receaued that lyuynge faythe, whyche onlye iuſtifieth, but rather a certayne knowelege, newe opinion or hyſtoricall fayth, whych dothe not chaunge the harte, nor quycken any newe affection. And by<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>cauſe they feele not a ſtudie, and wil to ſtryue agaynſte ther olde luſtes, they maye well perceaue, that they haue receaued no newe ſprete. But yet they ſaye and thynke that they beleue perfytly, &amp; then they ſlau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>der, and blaſpheme the treweth, ſaieng: that faythe onlye doth not iuſtifye.
<pb facs="tcp:5195:19"/> And ſo they returne to workes, to be iuſtifyed by them, daylye wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kynge, and yet neuer felyng, or per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceauynge any alteration of mynde, wyl, loue, or affection. All the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, whyche they do, they worke them only, bycauſe they wold haue a better thyng for theyr worke. And ſo they be hyrelynges and worke no thynge for loue, but for rewarde, &amp; wages, or elles at the leſt wyth ther workes, they wolde pacifie goddes wrath, and obteyne goddes fauour, and ſo robbe Chryſte of hys glorye. whyche by hys Prophete ſaythe:<note place="margin">Eſay. xlvi.</note> I wil not gyue my glory to any other. For Chriſt onlye wyth hys paſſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, and deathe dyd pacifie hys fathers wrath, as the ſcripture wytneſſeth: ſayeng thys is my welbeloued ſone,<note place="margin">Math. iii.</note> in whom I am well pleaſed.</p>
            <p>But whan the faythfull allege
<pb facs="tcp:5195:19"/> the ſcriptures, ſayenge that a man is not iuſtified, by the deades of the law, but by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faith of Ieſu Chriſt, as Paul ſaith:<note place="margin">Galath. ii.</note> y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> iuſticiaries to that aunſwere, that Paul meaneth by y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> texte, that man is not iuſtified by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> deades, or ceremonies of the lawe. And they further ſaye, that all they whyche worke the workes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maun<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ded by the decaloge, whyche is the law of the ten commaundementes, be by the workyng of the ſayde wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes iuſtified. To the whiche the faithfull ſaye, that yf anye workes myght iuſtifie, then the ceremonies of the lawe ſhulde iuſtifie, becauſe the ceremonies were commaunded of God, to be done for ſatiſfaction, and to make atoneme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t for ſynne, as it apeareth in manye places of the olde teſtament, and ſpecially Leui. primo, where it is wrytten in thys
<pb facs="tcp:5195:20"/> fourme: And he ſhall put his hande vpon the head of the brent ſacrifice, and it ſhalbe accepted for hym to be hys atonement.<note place="margin">For the lawe, whiche hathe but the ſhad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe of good thinges to come &amp; not the thinges in theyr own fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhion can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer with the ſacrifice whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che they offer yere by yere, continuallye make the co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers therto perfect. Hebr. x.</note> And yet theſe cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies dyd not iuſtifie, as the iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciaries affyrme, as it apereth Hebre. vij. &amp; .x. And the lawe of the ten com<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>maundementes, was not gyuen of God to iuſtifie, or to ſatyſfie for ſyn, but rather to condempne, and to ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forthe ſynne, wherby man myght knowe hys ſynnefull nature, and ſo flye to Chriſte. The lawe, ſaythe Paule, meaning the lawe called the decaloge, was geuen to punyſhe tranſgreſſours, and not that by the workes therof, the workers ſhulde be iuſtified. For durynge thys mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tall lyfe, there is no man hauynge our corruptible, weake, and ſynfull nature, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by any meanes fulfyl, &amp; do the workes of the lawe ſo perfyt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye,
<pb facs="tcp:5195:20"/> as the lawe requyreth them to be done. And where vnperfytnes is there is not, nor canne not be a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruynge of grace, and fauoure, but rather of punyſhement. Paul ſayth, that whyche was impoſſible to the lawe, in aſmuche as it was weake, thorough the fleſhe, that perfour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med God, and ſent hys ſone in the ſimilitude of ſynfull freſſhe, and by ſynne dampned ſynne, in the fleſhe, that the ryghtuouſnes re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired of the lawe, myght be ful<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fylled in them, which walke not af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter the fleſſhe, but after the ſpryte. If Paule ſaye, it was impoſſyble for the lawe to iuſtifie, bycauſe the fleſſhe was weake, and not able to perfourme the ſame: Howe can the iuſticiaries affyrme, that the lawe, or any of her workes can, or maye iuſtifie? Abraham beleued God, and
<pb facs="tcp:5195:21"/> it was counted vnto him for ryght<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſenes. For the promeſſe y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> Abra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ham ſhulde be heyre of the worlde, was not gyuen to Abraham,<note place="margin">Rom. iiii.</note> or to his ſeed through the lawe, but tho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rough y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ryghtwyſenes, whiche co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meth of faithe. For yf they, whiche were of the lawe, be heyres, than is faythe but vayne, and the promeſſe of none effecte. Alſo when zacheus ſayde,<note place="margin">Luke. xix.</note> Lorde beholde I geue to the poore halfe my goodes, &amp; yf I haue done any man wrong, I wil reſtore hym foure folde, Ieſus ſayd not, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> health was comen thys daye vnto hys houſe, bycauſe of hys good workes, but becauſe he was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come the chylde of Abraham,<note place="margin">Math. iii.</note> that is to ſaye a faythfull beleuer. Alſo Paule ſaythe not of the deedes of ryghtuouſnes, whyche we haue wrought, but of his mercy he ſaued
<pb facs="tcp:5195:21"/> vs.<note place="margin">Rom. vi.</note> And the ſame apoſtle ſayethe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gain y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the rewarde of ſynne is deth, but he ſayeth not, that the rewarde of workes of the lawe, other cerimo<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>niall, or of the decaloge, is lyfe. But he concludeth, by the grace of God lyfe eternall to come, and that onely in Chriſt Ieſu our Lorde, and by no other meanes. Al the ſcriptures wit<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>neſſe the fame.</p>
            <p>And fyrſt Abacuc ſayeth,<note place="margin">Abacuc. ii.</note> the iuſt lyueth by hys fayth. Alſo yf Abraha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> were made righteous through wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes, then hath he wherin to reioyſe, but not before God.<note place="margin">Rom. iiii.</note> But what ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the ſcripture? Abraham beleued God, and that was counted to hym for ryghteouſnes. Iſrael folowyng y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> law of rightwyſenes, attained not to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe of ryghtwyſnes. why ſo? euen bycauſe they ſoughte it not out of fayth,<note place="margin">Rom. vi.</note> but as it were out of the de<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſeruyng
<pb facs="tcp:5195:22"/> of workes. By grace are ye ſaued through faythe, &amp; that not of your ſelues,<note place="margin">Epheſ. ii.</note> for it is the gyfte of god &amp; not of workes, leſt any man ſhuld boſt hym ſelfe.</p>
            <p>By theſe authorities of holy ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ture, and innumerable more, to ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny here to wryte, it appereth that iu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſtifycation is attributed and geuen, truly &amp; only to fayth, &amp; y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> it is clerely and holy denyed any iuſtifycation to be geuen to workes. But ſuch me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> (ſayeth Paule) as knowe not the iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice of god,<note place="margin">Rom. x.</note> and continually ſearche and labour to ſet forth and ſtablyſhe theyr owne ryghtwyſenes, be neuer ſubiecte to the ryghtwyſenes, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che god aloweth. No, no, the na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>turall men do not perceyue thoſe thynges whych perteyne to god, for it is foolyſhnes to them.<note place="margin">i. Cor. ii.</note> Nother can man perceyue whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> he is ſpiritually
<pb facs="tcp:5195:22"/> examined, and therfore the iuſticia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ries readynge the .x. chapter of Mat<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>thew, thynke that it maketh muche for them, whych wel perceyued and vnderſtande maketh muche againſt them. Thys is the ſtorye.</p>
            <p>One came and ſayd vnto Chriſt, good maſter what thynge ſhal I do that I maye haue eternall lyfe? He ſayde vnto hym: why calleſt thou me good? there is none good but one, and that is god. But yf thou wylte enter into lyfe, kepe the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>maundementes. He ſayde whiche? and Ieſus ſayd thou ſhalt not kyll, thou ſhalte not breake wedlocke, thou ſhalte not ſteale, thou ſhalte not beare falſe wytnes, honour thy father &amp; mother, and y<hi rend="sup">u</hi> ſhalt loue thy neghbour as thy ſelfe. The yo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ge ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſayd vnto hym. I haue obſerued all theſe thynges from my youth, what
<pb facs="tcp:5195:23"/> haue I more to do? Ieſus ſayde vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to hym. Yf thou wylte be perfyte, go ſell that thou haſt, and geue it to the poore, and thou ſhalt haue treaſure in heuen, and come and folowe me. when the yonge ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> herde that ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eng, he went awaye mournyng, for he had great poſſeſſions.</p>
            <p>The condicion of all ypocrites here appereth, how they be euer bu<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ſye to do works, truſting in y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſame, nothyng regardyng w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> what herte, loue, &amp; mynde, they ſhal acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plyſhe &amp; fynyſhe them. Is it not great folyſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes to labour for y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> frute, before the tree ſpryng vp? So vnwyſe a thing it is to ſtudy and to labour to do the workes of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe, before they know howe to fulfyll the lawe truly. For Paule ſayeth,<note place="margin">Rom. vii.</note> y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> the law is ſpiritual, &amp; can neuer be truely perfourmed &amp; fulfylled w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> outwarde dede, excepte
<pb facs="tcp:5195:23"/> the inward loue &amp; affectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be purged &amp; made ſpiritual, by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſprite of god</p>
            <p>wherfore thys wyſe ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of lawe, in godlye &amp; ſpirituall thynges was but a foole, for he ſhulde fyrſte haue aſked, by what meanes he might ha<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ue fulfylled the law perfitly. But to hys vngodly queſtion, whych was, what he ſhulde do &amp; worke to haue eternal lyfe, ſuppoſing lyfe to be gy<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>uen by workes, &amp; not frely by grace: Chriſt anſwered him ſo, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> he might perceyue, that he coulde not fulfyl y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lawe, nor perfourme y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> workes ther<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>of. Notwythſtandyng he myndyng to iuſtifye hymſelfe, dyd go awaye, as blynde as he came. And ſo do all iuſticiaries, whyche thynke y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> they can fulfyl the lawe, &amp; workes therof perfytly, during this mortal lyfe. In the whych although the holy gooſt be gyue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vnto me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, yet bycauſe of oure
<pb facs="tcp:5195:24"/> ſynfull nature, we be ſo weake, that we can not perfourme the lawe per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fytlye. But the moſte perfyte man, ſhal complaine with Paule, ſayeng: the good whych I wolde do, I do not, and the euyll that I wolde not do, that I do. Who ſhal deliuer me, from thys bodye of deathe? The grace of God, by Ieſu Chriſt.</p>
            <p>Theſe blynde iuſticiaries, do not fele the corruption of our ſynful na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, poyſoned by the inobedience of oure father Adam, in ſo muche that the ſcripture,<note place="margin">Math. ix.</note> reſembleth vs to mu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtye veſſelles, whyche wyll corrupte the beſt wyne that ſhalbe putte into them. So althoughe the holy gooſt, worke hys workes in vs, yet oure corrupte nature dothe ſo alter and corrupte them, that they be neuer done perfytlye, as the lawe requy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth them to be done by vs. That
<pb facs="tcp:5195:24"/> proueth well the Prophete Dauid,<note place="margin">Pſalm. xiii.</note> ſayenge: All haue gone oute of the waye, they be become vnprofytable, there is none that dothe good, no not one. Salomon ſayeth:<note place="margin">Eccleſ. vii.</note> there is not one iuſte man in the earthe, whyche doth good and ſynneth not. Alſo I ſaye ſayeth:<note place="margin">Eſaye. lxiiii.</note> all oure ryght<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wyſenes,<note place="margin">i. Iohn .i,</note> before God is lyke a filthy cloth. Saynt Ihon ſayeth that we be all ſynners. And he that ſayeth that he hath no ſynne, dothe lye and the trueth is not in hym.</p>
            <p>Yf we be ſynners,<note place="margin">Math. vii.</note> ſurely then be we an yll tree, whych as Chriſt ſayeth,<note place="margin">Luke. xvii.</note> can not bryng forth good frute. For when we haue done, al that we can do, yet be we vnprofytable ſeruau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tes, &amp; do but that, which is our duty to do.<note place="margin">Pſalm. cxlii.</note> Therfore the prophet prayeth y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> god wil not enter into iudgement
<pb facs="tcp:5195:25"/> wyth hys ſeruaunt, for no fleſhe ſhal be iuſtifyed in hys fyght.</p>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">Galath. iii.</note>For a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the ſcripture hath concluded all vnder ſynne, that the promyſe,<note place="margin">Rom. xi.</note> by the fayth in Ieſu Chriſt &amp; not for theyr workes, ſhuld be gy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen to the beleuers. They preſume to muche, whyche wyth theyr wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes wyll chalenge heauen for theyr rewarde, whych Chriſt only, ſo pain<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fully hath purchaſed already. They compare, &amp; make of lyke ſtrength &amp; vertue, Chriſtes blood &amp; theyr good workes. But ones they ſhall feale &amp; perceyue, that theyr good workes, be not worthy in value to co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teruaile &amp; pacifye goddes wrathe, other they wyll lacke perfection and goodnes, or els they wyll not be ſufficient in nombre.</p>
            <p>Thys is good cauſe, to make the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to dout. But yf good workes ſhould
<pb facs="tcp:5195:25"/> pacifye the fathers wrathe, then chriſt in vayne, hath ſuffred ſo great payne. Alſo they haue no promyſe made by god, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> good workes ſhall pacifye gods wrath, but rather to y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> contrary. As it appereth by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phete Eſay, ſayeng:<note place="margin">Eſaye. lvii.</note> I wyl ſhewe &amp; declare thy goodnes &amp; thy workes, but they ſhall not profyte the. And where is no promyſe of god, there can not be conſtant faith, &amp; where is not fayth, there remayneth vnbelefe &amp; myſtruſt: and where ſo euer is vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belefe, there foloweth eternal damp<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>nation, as Chriſt ſayeth, who ſo be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leueth not, ſhalbe condempned.</p>
            <p>Although al y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> ſcriptures declare thys to be true manifeſtly,<note place="margin">Marc. xvi.</note> yet there be many y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> this my ſente<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce wil be greatly offended, ſayeng: yf workes do not iuſtifye, why do the ſcriptu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>res commaunde them ſo earneſtlye
<pb facs="tcp:5195:26"/> to be done? To ſuche I aunſwere: that the ſcriptures commaunde, the workes of the lawe to be perfour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med and done, whyche be moſte perfyte and godly workes, bycauſe they be commaunded of God. Yet although they be as perfytly done, as man can deuyſe them to be done, they do not iuſtifye. For we be all vncleane whyche can brynge forthe nothynge cleane,<note place="margin">Iob, x.</note> as Iob ſayeth, who can make a cleane thynge, of that whyche is vncleane conceyued thorough mannes ſeede?<note place="margin">Math. xvi.</note> Alſo ſome allege this texte: The ſonne of man ſhall come in the glorye wyth hys aungels, and then ſhall rewarde e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerye man accordynge to hys wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes. To thys, I ſaye, that by thys texte and ſuche other, it appeareth that the ſcripture,<note place="margin">Deuter. vii. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="3 letters">
                     <desc>•••</desc>
                  </gap>ter. xvi.</note> threateneth more the vngodlye and theyr euell wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes,
<pb facs="tcp:5195:26"/> then to promyſe rewarde of ioye, for the meryte of good wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes. And where the ſcripture ſoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth, to gyue rewarde of honoure and glorye, to them whyche per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeuer in well doynge, there is no rewarde promyſed to the workes, but to the worker: not for the wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes ſake, but yet accordynge as the workes do wytneſſe, and teſtifye of the man, which dyd worke them. It is out of order, to prayſe the frute be<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fore the tree, for the tree maketh the frute good, &amp; the frute not the tree, but only declareth and wytneſſeth the goodnes or ylneſſe of the tree.</p>
            <p>By what more laufull wayes and meanes, maye a man condempne a lyer, then by the vntrewe wordes whyche he hathe ſpoken, tryed a<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>gaynſt him? And forthermore good
<pb facs="tcp:5195:27"/> wordes and workes, and the euyll wordes &amp; workes, whyche we haue ſpoken and done, ſhalbe ſure proues and wytneſſes, other with vs, or els againſt vs, at the general iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t accordynge to the whych we ſhal re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ceyue. Yf they be good workes, that we haue wrought, then wyll they wytnes, that we be y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> faythful chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren of god, to whome of ryght be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>belongeth, the enheritau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; goodes of oure father, before that we can worke of deſerue it. For the chyl<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren do enheryte theyr fathers lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>des and goodes, and not the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uauntes. And the chyldren do not deſerue the inheritaunce, but god re<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>wardeth them wyth eternall lyfe, whyche he gaue them, longe before they coulde worke, as it appeareth Geneſis .xxii. and .xv. And although the ſcriptures promyſe a reward to
<pb facs="tcp:5195:27"/> well workers, yet it promyſeth not eternall lyfe, as a rewarde, deſerued by y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> workes, and ſo due vnto them: for that is only the reward, purcha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed by Chriſtes death, &amp; frely gyuen before any man can worke. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore let eternal lyfe, remyſſion of our ſynnes, and iuſtifycation, be onelye the reward lyberally gyuen by god, onely for Chriſtes ſake. And then gyue to workes, all the glorye that the ſcripture doth gyue, whyche, no doute, to good workes gyueth ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny prayſes, &amp; as well temporall, as ſpiritual graces.</p>
            <p>Wherfore for the good frute and greate goodnes, whych do enſue &amp; folowe good workes, euerye chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſten man wyll exercyſe good wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes.</p>
            <p>An other nomber therbe, whyche euer haue in theyr mouthes, thys
<pb facs="tcp:5195:28"/> propoſition: fayth onely iuſtifyeth, whyche neuer taſted in theyr harte, any parte of that lyuyng fayth, whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che onely iuſtifyeth. Suche thoſe be, whyche vſe a beeſtlye, and not a godlye lybertye, in the eatynge of meates,<note place="margin">Galat. v.</note> whome Paule reproued, ſayenge: gyue not youre lybertye to be an occaſion of luſte. They forbeare no kynde of meates and drynkes at any tyme,<note place="margin">Math. xv.</note> ſayenge: that whyche entreth into the mouthe, dothe not defyle a man, nothynge felynge or perceyuynge theyr wan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ton luſtes, whyche rage in theyr har<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tes (more then any nede to eate) and defyle the inwarde man. They remembre not thys texte, whether ye eate or drynke,<note place="margin">i. Cor. x.</note> or do any other thynge,<note place="margin">Colloſ. iii.</note> do it in the name of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> lorde God dyd not ordeyne thynges to ſa<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>tiſfye luſtes, but to ſocoure nede.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5195:28"/>
            <p>Theſe kynde of people faſt not, for that wyl hurte theyr co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>plexio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; alſo theyr god theyr belye wyll neuer ſuf<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>fer them to be quiete, vntyl he be ful &amp; wel ſerued. Deale almes they wyl not, for feare the people ſhuld ſe the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; they alſo glorye &amp; reioyce in theyr good dede, &amp; ſo, greuouſly offende in hypocriſye. And praye they wyll not, for feare they ſhulde offende w<hi rend="sup">t</hi> much ſpeaking, as y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> heathe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> dyd. For a co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cluſion, ther is no kynde of luſt, but they wyl taſte it, &amp; the good wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kes co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ded by god, wyll they not do, truſtyng onelye to theyr fayned fayth, &amp; falſe confydence, that it wyl ſaue them, and couer all theyr wyc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ked luſtes, at the general iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t.</p>
            <p>Theſe delicate and pleaſau<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtians,<note place="margin">Iames. ii.</note> ſaynt Iames reproueth ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>enge: what auayleth it my brethren thoughe a man ſaye he hath faythe,
<pb facs="tcp:5195:29"/> when he hathe no dedes? wylt thou vnderſtande, o thou vayne ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that fayth wythout dedes is deade? But ſuche wanton chriſtians, had nede of a fayth to iuſtifye them, whyche may not be ſhewed &amp; tryed by theyr workes, for theyr workes be ſuche, that they be aſhamed of them, that they ſhuld be other ſene or knowen, or els they wyl do no good workes, ne leſt they ſhuld haue confidence to be ſaued by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. And lyke as to haue confidence in good workes, to be iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtifyed by them, is erronious, ſo in lyke wyſe, to beleue that good wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes ſhall not be rewarded of god, is deuylyſhe and dampnable. But yet the ſcriptures ſeme, oftentymes to attribute &amp; gyue eternal lyfe, to wor<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>kers of good workes as a rewarde and ſometyme to workes. But well conſydered, it is not for the workes
<pb facs="tcp:5195:29"/> ſake, as deſerued thereby. But eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall lyfe, is a reward frelygyuen by God to al the faythful for Chriſtes ſake only, which benefyte well per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceaued, taſted &amp; feled in our hertes, wyll cauſe vs to worke wyth loue erneſtly, bycauſe we haue receyued frely, through Chriſtes deſeruyng, eternall lyfe. And not bycauſe we ſhall receyue eternal lyfe, for the de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeruyng of our workes. For ſo wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes ſhulde be iniuriouſe to Chriſtes bloode and death, whych onlye is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> price of eternall lyfe. Alſo the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures apere to attribute eternal life to good workes, to moue &amp; to ſteare other, diligentlye to worke good workes. And bycauſe the workes of the faythfull, be ſene of men, and the inwarde faith canne not be out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wardly ſene, &amp; perceaued, therefore the ſcripture applieth eternall lyfe
<pb facs="tcp:5195:30"/> to workes, as to the cauſe, whyche truely examyned, be but the effecte of faith, which is y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> very true cauſe. And although, no dowte, to good workes manye &amp; greate rewardes be due as wel te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>porall as ſpirituall: Yet all the places, whyche ſound to gyue eternal lyfe, as a reward other to good workers or to good workes muſt be vnderſtande, as I haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſhewed, or elles they ſhal cauſe workes to be eſtemed better, than they in trueth be, or can be proued, and alſo ſhal cauſe Chriſtes bloode, to be of lytle reputacion. Wherfore that euerye good Chriſtian, maye walke the true waye, nothynge tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtynge to haue remiſſion of his ſyn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes for his good workes, which on<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>ly perteyneth to God, &amp; is hys only gyfte, nor to thynke y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good workes ſhalbe vnrewarded by God, whoſe
<pb facs="tcp:5195:30"/> reward excedeth al ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s vnderſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dynge &amp; knowlege. I wyll declare therefore ſome cauſes, why good kes ſhuld be done.</p>
            <p>Firſt,<note place="margin">ii. Pet. i.</note> that they maye wytneſſe to vs certaynly, that oure fayth is ly<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uynge, and not deade. For a lyuyng tree, wyll bryng forth frute, in tyme and ſeaſon.<note place="margin">Math. v.</note> Secondelye that other ſeyng our good workes, may be ꝓuoked to do alſo good workes.</p>
            <p>Thyrdlye,<note place="margin">Luke .xvi.</note> we muſt do good wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, to rendre &amp; gyue acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ptes, of y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> talent to vs from God co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mytted.</p>
            <p>Fourthly,<note place="margin">i. Petri. ii.</note> that through oure good workes, our heuenly father may be glorified. Fyftely,<note place="margin">Eſay. lvii. Rom. xiiii. i. Cor. x.</note> leſt through our euil workes, we be offence to other.</p>
            <p>Syxtely,<note place="margin">Epheſ. ii.</note> of dutye we be bound to worke well, for therefore we be iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtified, that we myght and ſhulde worke well.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5195:31"/>
            <p>
               <note place="margin">ii. Petri. i.</note>Seue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>thlye, God which did geue al thynges,<note place="margin">Pſal. xxxiii.</note> commaundeth vs to do wel, ſayenge: declyne fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euyll, &amp; do good. Now it apereth, y<hi rend="sup">e</hi> good wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes be to be done, as frutes of iuſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ce, which not withſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dyng make no man iuſte, but witneſſe that he is iuſte. Alſo it is euide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, that a liuyng fayth, which euer worketh by loue, doth onlye iuſtifie, &amp; alſo ſuch wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes, as ſpryng out of a lyuing faith, ſhal not be vnrewarded, &amp; that with great rewardes. And the workes do teſtifie, that thys fayth, is a lyuyng faith. The workes, which this faith euer bryngethe forthe, be theſe. To feare and to loue God, to loue hys neybour, co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tinuallye to crucifye the fleſhe with al her luſtes. And as he dayly ſynneth, ſo he dayly lame<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>teth, aſkyng God forgeueneſſe there of, ſtudyenge euer, howe to reſyſte the
<pb facs="tcp:5195:31"/> ſame, &amp; all occaſions thereof, &amp; alſo prayeth God daylye, to geue hym grace to reſiſte ſynne. And bycauſe he feleth in hym ſelfe, y<hi rend="sup">t</hi> al his good thoughtes, wylles &amp; deades be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfyt, &amp; lacke the goodnes whyche the lawe requireth in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, therfore he knowelegeth hys good deades, and thoughtes, to be ſynfull &amp; conti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nually prayeth God, to forgeue and to pardon the ſynfulnes of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Ney<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he aſcribeth, nor imputeth, any iuſtification, to hys good workes, but rather flyeth to Gods mercye, which is promiſed to al true repen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters, for Chryſtes bloode ſake, tru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtynge therby conſtantly, and ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore only, to haue eternall lyfe.</p>
            <p>And as touchyng good workes, he is glad euer whan occaſio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> is ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen, to worke them, as well as he can, and ſoroweth, that he can not
<pb facs="tcp:5195:32"/> do the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> with more perfytneſſe &amp; loue: But as perfytly as he can, he dothe them, hauynge reſpecte, onlye to the good will, great mercy and fauour, which God for Chriſtes ſake hathe ſhewed on hym, in forgeuynge hym hys ſynnes. He thynketh him bound of duetie, for loue to do the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſo that hys workes ſpryng out of a louyng herte, remembrynge the loue, which God hath before ſhewed, in gyuyng hym eternall lyfe freelye.</p>
            <p>Nowe it apereth, that good wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kes ſprynge forth of a louyng hart, whyche no man canne haue, except he fyrſte beleue, that God for verye loue, which he beareth to hym, for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geuethe hym all hys ſynnes, &amp; that frelye for Chriſtes ſake, who is hys iuſtice, ſatiſfaction, holynes and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>demption.</p>
            <p>After this ſort and good faſhion,
<pb facs="tcp:5195:32"/> I wolde that all Chriſtians ſhulde do ther good workes, for loue whi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>che they bere to God, for the great and ineſtimable benefytes (whiche they vndeſerued of theyr part) haue receaued of God, and not for anye thynge, whyche they wolde for theyr workes ſake, or worthynes, receaue of God. For than, there en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tent and workynge, is grounded vpon the loue of theyr ſelfe, and not vpon the loue of God, and ſo be no good workes, but vnparfyt and full of ſynne. And ſo thys declara<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of iuſtification by faythe, and of the efficacitie and ſtrengthe of good workes, is a ſuffycient doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tryne, I truſte, to all the faythfull.</p>
            <p>And as to them whoſe eyes be cloſed, and made blynde, and whoſe hartes be hardened, I dyd not
<pb facs="tcp:5195:33"/> mynde to wryte, but in the mean ſeaſon, I wyll praye to God at hys good wyll and pleaſure, to open theyr eyes, and to mollifye the hartes, that they may be conuert<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> and that he maye make them hole, of whome onlye all healthe is, to whome be all honour and glorye. AMEN.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:5195:33"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
